<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-18T13:28:24-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">William An</title><subtitle>My portfolio</subtitle><entry><title type="html">SDMTS Part 1 Static Data Preview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/SDMTS-Part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SDMTS Part 1 Static Data Preview" /><published>2017-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/SDMTS-Part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/SDMTS-Part-1/">&lt;p&gt;In this series I will be looking at the data provided 
by the San Diego Metropolitan Transit System. This 
section will be a quick look at the static data, the
data that provides the schedule and route information. 
 &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;important-links&quot;&gt;Important Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notebooks that supplement the series can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wnanpi95/SDMTS_DataAnalysis&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the SDMTS data is available on their 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdmts.com/business-center/developers&quot;&gt;developer&lt;/a&gt;
page, although a key will have to be requested for 
access to their real time feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SDMTS bus system has always held a special place in my
heart. Since I didn’t have a car throughout my UCSD career,
the buses provided the life line I needed to get away from
campus any time I needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part, we will take a quick look through what sort
of information is available. The R notebook that supplements
this post can be found in the Part_1 folder of the repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The static data set follows the GTFS spec established by 
google. A complete and thorough reference can be found on 
their &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notebook will simply explore the most interesting 
sections of the data, as well as the part most relevant to
the later parts of the series. Let’s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-files&quot;&gt;The Files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The static information comes in the form of fifteen files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Agency&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Calendar Dates&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Calendar&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Fare Attributes&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Fare Rules&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Feed Info&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Frequencies&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place Patterns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Places&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Routes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shapes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop Times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Transfers&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first seven files and transfers will be excluded from 
this analysis.All of the files come in the form of a csv. 
I will briefly summarize the data found in each file, as will 
be relevant to our use case. The exact information found in
each file can be explored in the notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;places&quot;&gt;Places&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This file provides a list of locations (think street corners
and prominent landmarks) by name, coordinates (latitude and
longitude). Each place is assigned a 6 character id, which
is used in the next file…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;place-patterns&quot;&gt;Place Patterns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data here is subset by a route and direction. Each subset
consists of an ordered list of places (provided by id) visited
by each route-direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;routes&quot;&gt;Routes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we find the association between route number and it’s
long name (two locations that describe its range). In addition
we can also find here if the route travels in more than one
directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;shapes&quot;&gt;Shapes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to properly map the trips the bus takes, we need to
account for the roads that will be taken, as well as their
curvature. In this file, we find subsets defined by a shape id
which consists of three numbers separated by underscores. The
first number is the route associated with the shape id, while
the next two describe the direction and variation of the 
specific trip that it describes. Each subset consists of a 
sequence of coordinates, as well as the distance traveled
by the bus once it has reached that point in the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;stops&quot;&gt;Stops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This file provides a list of bus stops, by name and 
coordinates, and assigns each stop an id, which is used in…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;stop-times&quot;&gt;Stop Times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are first introduced to the concept of trip ids here. Each
trip id uniquely defines a combination of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;route&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;departure time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the file contains the arrival and departure time
at each stop, per trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;trips&quot;&gt;Trips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, each trip id is associated with all of the characteristics defined above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;visualization-of-file-relations&quot;&gt;Visualization of file relations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script to set up the postgresql database can be found in the repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;Static_Info_Relation.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Created with pgadmin 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this was a clear summary of the kind of data we will be working with.
In the part 2, we will dive into the data a bit, to get a more concrete idea
of the data at hand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this series I will be looking at the data provided by the San Diego Metropolitan Transit System. This section will be a quick look at the static data, the data that provides the schedule and route information.</summary></entry></feed>